boones Thank You mr. speaker I'd like to
acknowledge first the role that Craig
Foss as chair of the Finance and
expenditure committee himself played in
this bill and it did indeed steer
through the Civic committee well I don't
want to go too far I'd like to comment
about the background to the bill about a
particular aspect of it which as my
colleague David Cunliffe has indicated
we as the Labor members on that
committee will be watching to ensure
that it works and the site in the way
that the Reserve Bank has assured it it
will work and to look at a missed
opportunity in respect of this bill also
the background to this bill was of
course the collapse of financial markets
two years ago in the United States
spreading across the rest of the world
and of course we have seen in this
country moves to reinforce regulation
around how banks and financial
institutions operate and of course it
left the question of where the insurance
industry was and indeed although the
insurance industry itself in New Zealand
was not in any distress the global
financial crisis illustrated very
clearly the vulnerability of the
financial sector as a whole and hence
this bill emerged through that process
the bill requires of insurers operating
in the New Zealand market to be licensed
and supervised by the Reserve Bank and
to comply with minimum Prudential
requirements compliance is going to be
largely self administered under the bill
but the reserve bank has an important
supervisory role and the Labor Party
supports the bill but one comment we
would make is that doesn't go far enough
dealing with one of the key economic
issues that we face as a nation and that
is the need to put exporters at the
center of monetary policy and if we
needed a further illustration of that
today I guess it came in the
announcement not unexpected from the
Reserve Bank governor that we're going
to see the official cash rate go up
another point 25 basis points to three
percent a not unexpected decision but
one which reflects back on our current
monetary policy settings indeed the
Reserve Bank governor has little choice
given the focus of the contact he must
reflect
his concerns for the future rise of
inflation that's the only policy setting
he has to pay any real regard to and
we've note only in the last three weeks
the Prime Minister was in my electorate
and Christchurch central addressing a
forum of exporters in which he stood up
and said with some audacity I'd have to
say that the monetary policies of this
country were quote unquote the best in
the world and of the best in the world
means that our exporters continue to get
stick because of the settings of
monetary policies that we see dollars we
have indicated very clearly phil golf
has given the speech which the prime
minister chose to pan that we should be
looking at monetary policy settings and
there and we can be payback we have
indicated i wish to be bipartisan on
many measures within this bill but we
can't let to go without any commentary
suggesting that if we're going to be
bipartisan on the future of the industry
insurance industry then why can't we be
bipartisan on the monetary policy which
the exporter's of this nation are
telling MPs like Jonathan Coleman every
day and his electorate that is its it's
actually screwing the scrum and respect
of their capacity to export and earn for
this nation there is no one magic bullet
on monetary policy but there is a need
to review the settings as Australia has
done and we often from the other side of
the house hear about how we want to
catch up with Australia indicated in the
last couple of days of course how well
or not we're doing in respect of that
but Australian Reserve Bank looks at a
number of factors including the
inflation rate it looks at the whole
issue of the state of the economy it
looks at employment it looks at the
dollar it looks at the health of the
economy those are important factors when
we are considering the role of the
Reserve Bank and monetary policy
settings and therefore we say this was
another opportunity which the government
has missed where it could have widened
could have looked at the issue of
monetary policy and take take taken a
decision to review this current
obsession with inflation not that this
is not a crucial
factor and economic settings but you
can't play the whole game on 11 ruling
and that's why we say we had an
opportunity here and and the
opportunities are still in front of
government and it is disappointing to
see that when Phil Goff gives a speech
which says we could consider a review of
monetary policy there is an instinctive
response to that to baguette and the
Prime Minister has the audacity to stand
up until a Canterbury exporting audience
that the dollar at the monetary policy
setting is the best in the world and we
see the results today with presumably a
rising dollar and rising interest rates
well let's return to the substance of
the bill which is indeed around the
issues of Prudential supervision of our
insurance industry and one of the key
elements of the bill is around the
impacts on New Zealand and overseas
insurers who are covered by the
extension of Prudential frameworks and
most particularly the questions around
whether this bill would disadvantage new
zealand-based insurers who are subject
to the regime's whereas a an Australian
or a insurance company based in another
company which meets the agreed
requirements of the Reserve Bank can
operate under the Prudential regime of
that host country and I do have to
disagree in part at least with the
Minister of Finance who affirmed in his
comments on the bill earlier that there
was no real cost involved for our
insurance companies to meet this bill we
did have a submission from ami insurance
which is New Zealand's largest new
zealand-based insurance company which
suggested that the costs are meeting the
new Prudential regime meeting the cost
of those new capital adequacy ratios was
of the order of 35 million dollars which
is not a sum to be sneezed at even for a
relatively large corporate like pretty
late am I which I think most New
Zealanders would acknowledge as a very
good insurance company wisely based in
Christchurch central electorate the we
were assured however by the Reserve Bank
officials and the committee said spent
considerable time on these issues
that the regime as as proposed in the
bill was not going to disadvantage New
Zealand insurers that we're going to be
exemptions there are exemptions in the
bill in relation to a number of clauses
for overseas-based insurance companies
but those would only be granted if the
insurance company operating from
overseas was subject to home
jurisdiction and in relation to the that
met the standards of the reserve bank
and that taken at a whole the regime
that those foreign-based museum these
foreign based companies would actually
meet the standards of the Reserve Bank's
Prudential regime regime we did as i
mentioned do did have some concerns
still expressed by entities including am
i who noted the difference in capital
adequacy ratios between Australia
specifically and New Zealand quite quite
a difference on various aspects of
investment but we will be born we will
be monitoring how this works will be
wanting to see if the Reserve Bank's
assurances are in fact borne out as as
the legislation takes effect on the
industry makes its changes I mean
obviously when the great concerns is
that we have at the moment a great bleed
of of capital goes on our current
account balance has never been in the
black since I was a schoolboy which is a
wee while ago and we will be obviously
watching to see whether overseas-based
insurance companies do do come back and
and use the bill and respect of whether
they can take further insurance monies
back out of the country back out of the
country that should be a concern to
members opposite when we do have a
current account balance which has been
in the red which is heading further into
the red this is an issue that New
Zealand Inc needs to take note of we
know that we need to have regulation of
financial markets Labour's never been
shy of regulating financial markets or
any markets but some members opposite
don't believe in regulation they don't
know the market will always rule good to
see we can get something census I
a point of order honorable steve
sheppard i'm sorry mr. speaker but i
cannot hear my colleague even speak what
the interjections coming from you that's
a fair comment and I have raised this
point before that we should be listening
if you want to interject against the
speaker that's fine but this cross
bearing of other points that have got no
relationship to the debate are
unacceptable who bring them birds you
have a minute ten remaining thank you
mr. speaker s are saying the point about
regulation is it needs to be judicious
needs to make sure that it works in the
interests of New Zealand and so we will
be watching to ensure that the
exemptions that have been provided by
this legislation to overseas insurers us
insurers do not do so any disadvantage
relative to New Zealand insurers which
have to meet the new zealand Reserve
Bank's requirements on balance that was
the decision the comedic the exemptions
that are in the R&D at the law in front
of us there because a strong argument
emerged about not duplicating regimes in
one country and another we were advised
the duplication from the Australian
regime for example would be
inappropriate to have it in both
countries we've accepted